A Guide to the Papers of Samuel X. Radbill 1961-1967, [n.d.]
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
Papers of Samuel X. Radbill 1961-1967, [n.d.]
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-9
2.5 linear feet, 6 boxes: 13 cm x 39.5 cm x 26.5 cm. Processed materials total 405 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Papers of Samuel X. Radbill were purchased and donated to the Library in 2004 by Robert L. Chevalier, M.D., Benjamin Armistead Shepherd Professor of Pediatrics and Chair of the Department of Pediatrics at the University of Virginia School of Medicine.
Biographical/Historical Information
Samuel X. Radbill was born in Philadelphia in 1901. He was educated in the Philadelphia public schools and received his medical degree from the University of Pennsylvania School of Medicine in 1924. On December 27, 1925 he married Frances Hoffman. On June 1, 1926 he moved into 7043 Elmwood Avenue, in the Eastwick Section of Philadelphia, where he had his home and his office. His wife, a nurse, assisted him in his practice. He practiced in this office until his retirement in 1982. In 1938 he was certified as a pediatrician and provided pediatric services at Children's Hospital and Philadelphia General Hospital. He died in November 1987.
Radbill was a dedicated clinician, but he also was a scholar and a medical historian. Throughout his career he lectured and authored over several hundred reviews, articles, and books about medical history. Radbill actively collected books, physicians' book plates, and pediatric implements.
Scope and Content
This collection is composed of Radbill's drafts, footnotes, and manuscript for the book, "The Autobiographical Ana of Robley Dunglison, M.D." published by the American Philosophical Society, December 1963. Robley Dunglison (1798-1969) was brought from England to Charlottesville, Virginia by Thomas Jefferson to serve as the first full-time Professor of Medicine at the University of Virginia in 1825. Dunglison left in 1833 to teach at the University of Maryland. In 1836 he moved to Philadelphia and continued his career at Jefferson Medical College of Philadelphia. Dunglison was one of the more eminent and nationally recognized medical figures of his time.
In 1852 Dungison prepared his "Ana" in order to preserve his personal recollections. He included letters and other records to personally document his memories. As the editor, Radbill organized Dunglison's work, wrote the introduction, and added footnotes to emphasize medical schools, medical education, medical literature, and also to identify the numerous individuals mentioned in Robley's text.
Arrangement
This collection was removed from 8 large binders and one box. Information from each binder was kept in order, but divided into folders using the published book as a reference guide.
Contents List
- Title Page & Table of Contents for Duniglison's Ana [n.d.], 2 TD, 1 AD, 1 TMs w/AN (Box-folder 001-001)
  Re: Handwritten edits.
- Introduction [n.d.], 1 TMs, 8 AD (Box-folder 001-002)
  Re: Radbill's typed introduction to Ana, with handwritten edits and notes.
- Portraits [n.d.], 1 AD (Box-folder 001-003)
  Re: Handwritten discussion of Dunglinson's portraits.
- Acknowledgements [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 001-004)
- Adversaria [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN, 3 AN (Box-folder 001-005)
  Re: Typed manuscript with handwritten edits of the first chapter, "The Formatives Years," of the published book.
- Volume II [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN, 1 AN (Box-folder 001-006)
  Re: Typed manuscript with edits for the second chapter, "The University & Thomas Jefferson," in the published book.
- Volume II (cont.) [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN (Box-folder 001-007)
  Re: Typed manuscript with edits for the third chapter, "Virginia Reminiscences," in the published book.
- Volume II (cont.) [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN, 2 AN (Box-folder 001-008)
  Re: Typed manuscript with edits for the fourth chapter, "The University of Maryland," in the published book.
- Volume II (cont.) [n.d.], 1 TMs w/ AN (Box-folder 001-009)
  Re: Typed manuscript with edits for the fifth chapter, "Jefferson Medical College," in the published book.
- Volume II (cont.) [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN (Box-folder 001-010)
  Re: Typed manuscript with edits for the sixth chapter, "Philadelphia Days," in the published book.
- Index to the first seven volumes of Ana [n.d.], 1 TMs w/ AN (Box-folder 001-011)
  Re: In Alphabetical order.
- Page Proof Index [n.d.], 1 AN, 1 TMs w/AN (Box-folder 001-012)
  Re: Extensive corrections made to the Index.
- Index: A's - D's [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN, 1 AN (Box-folder 001-013)
- Index: E's - M's [n.d.], 1 TD w/ AN (Box-folder 001-014)
- Index: N's - Z's [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 001-015)
- Index: pgs 29-35 [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN (Box-folder 001-016)
- Index: "J's" [n.d.], 1 AD, 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 001-017)
- Note cards for Indexes [n.d.], 17 AN (Box-folder 001-018)
- Title Page: The Ana of Robley Dunglison, M.D., Notes [n.d.], 1 AD (Box-folder 002-001)
  Re: Handwritten title page.
- Title Page: The Ana of Robley Dunglison, M.D. [n.d.], 1 TD w/ AN (Box-folder 002-002)
  Re: Typed title page.
- Frontispiece [n.d.], 1 AD (Box-folder 002-003)
  Re: Handwritten text for caption under picture of Robley Dunglison.
- ANA [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 002-004)
  Re: Robley Dunglison describes his "private autobiographical Ana."
- Footnotes, Chapter I [n.d.], 1 TMs w/ AN (Box-folder 002-005)
  Re: Typed footnotes with handwritten edit for Chapter I, "The Formative Years," in the published book.
- Typed Manuscript with Footnotes: Adversaria, Chapter I ] [n.d.], 1 TMs w/ AN (Box-folder 002-006)
  Re: This typed manuscript with inserted slips of paper indicating footnotes, follows the first half of the first chapter, "The Formative Years," of the published book.
- Typed Manuscript with Footnotes: Adversaria, Chapter I (cont.) [n.d.], 1 TMs (Box-folder 002-007)
  Re: This typed manuscript with inserted slips of paper indicating footnotes, follows the second half of the first chapter, "The Formative Years," of the published book.
- Footnotes: Chapter II [n.d.], 2 AN (Box-folder 002-008)
  Re: Two loose leaf handwritten footnotes referring to Chapter II.
- Typed Manuscript with Footnotes: Chapter II [n.d.], 1 TMs w/ AN, 3 AN (Box-folder 002-009)
  Re: This typed manuscript with inserted slips of paper indicating footnotes, follows the first half of the second chapter, "The University of Virginia & Jefferson," of the published book.
- Typed Manuscript with Footnotes: Chapter II (cont.) [n.d.], 1 TMs w/ AN (Box-folder 002-010)
  Re: This typed manuscript with inserted slips of paper indicating footnotes, follows the second half of the second chapter, "The University of Virginia & Jefferson," of the published book. (It goes to p. 42, subtitle "University of Virignia Activities."
- Loose leaf miscellaneous pages [n.d.], 3 AN, 10 TD (Box-folder 002-011)
  Re: Deal with various footnotes.
- Card Catalogue Index: Autobiographical Ana [n.d.], 4 TN (photocopies) (Box-folder 002-012)
- Typed Manuscript & Footnotes: University of Virginia Activities (partial Ch, II) [n.d.], 1 TMs w/ AN (Box-folder 002-013)
  Re: Begins with subtitle "University of Virginia Activities" with inserted footnotes.
- Typed Manuscript & Footnotes: Chapter III [n.d.], 1 TMs w/ AN, 2 AD (Box-folder 002-014)
  Re: This typed manuscript with inserted slips of paper indicating footnotes, follows the first half of the third chapter, "Virginia Reminiscences," of the published book.
- Typed Manuscript & Footnotes: Chapter III (cont.) [n.d.], 1 TMs (Box-folder 002-015)
  Re: This typed manuscript with inserted slips of paper indicating footnotes, follows the second half of the third chapter, "Virginia Reminiscences," of the published book.
- Typed Manuscript & Footnotes: Chapter IV [n.d.], 1 TMs w/ AN, 1 AD (Box-folder 003-001)
  Re: This typed manuscript with inserted slips of paper indicating footnotes, follows the fourth chapter, "University of Maryland," of the published book, until the subtitle, "Changes in the University of Maryland."
- Footnotes: Chapter V [n.d.], 4 AD (Box-folder 003-002)
  Re: Handwritten footnotes for Chapter 5, "Jefferson Medical College" in the published book.
- Notes: Jefferson Papers of the University of Virginia [n.d.], 18 AN (Box-folder 003-003)
  Re: Radbill's handwritten notes.
- Letter from Elizabeth C. Litsinger to Florence R. Kirk August 22, 1961, 1 TL (Box-folder 003-004)
  Re: Description of the Philcretan Society.
- Typed Manuscript with Footnotes: [Chapter V] [n.d.], 1 TMs, 5 AN (Box-folder 003-005)
  Re: This typed manuscript with inserted slips of paper indicating footnotes, follows the first half of the fifth chapter, "Jefferson Medical College," of the published book.
- Typed Manuscript with Footnotes: [Chapter V] (cont.) [n.d.], 1 TMs w/ AN, 9 AN (Box-folder 003-006)
  Re: This typed manuscript with inserted slips of paper indicating footnotes, follows the second half of the fifth chapter, "Jefferson Medical College," of the published book.
- Typed Manuscript with Footnotes: [Chapter VI] [n.d.], 1 TMs, 25 AN (Box-folder 003-007)
  Re: This typed manuscript with inserted slips of paper indicating footnotes, follows the first half of the sixth chapter, "Philadelphia Days," of the published book.
- Typed Manuscript with Footnotes: [Chapter VI] (cont.) [n.d.], 1 TMs w/ AN (Box-folder 003-008)
  Re: This typed manuscript with inserted slips of paper indicating footnotes, follows the second half of the sixth chapter, "Philadelphia Days," of the published book.
- Footnotes: [Chapter I, The Formative Years] [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN (Box-folder 004-001)
  Re: Heavily edited footnotes.
- Footnotes: [Chapter II, The University of Virginia & Jefferson] [n.d.], 1 TMs w/ AN (Box-folder 004-002)
- Footnotes: [Chapter III, Virginia Reminiscences] [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN (Box-folder 004-003)
- Footnotes: [Chapter IV, The University of Maryland] [n.d.], 1 TMs w/ AN (Box-folder 004-004)
- Footnotes: [Chapter VI, Philadelphia Days] [n.d.], 1 TMs w/ AN (Box-folder 004-005)
- Footnotes: [Chapter VII, Life's Zenith] [n.d.], 1 TMs w/ AN (Box-folder 004-006)
- Footnotes: Miscellaneous [n.d.], 11 AN, 21 TD w/ AN (Box-folder 004-007)
  Re: Possibly footnotes that Radbill chose not to place in the book.
- Transcribed letters written by Robley Dunglison [n.d.], 3 TD (Box-folder 004-008)
  Re: Transcribed letters that Dunglison wrote about Dr. Beaumont in 1832 and 1833.
- Handwritten notes [n.d.], 4 AN, 1 TN w/AN (Box-folder 004-009)
- Notes: Nathan Ryno Smith [n.d.], 2 TD, 2 AD (Box-folder 004-010)
- Handwritten Notes [n.d.], 4 AD (Box-folder 004-011)
- Transcribed letters written by Robley Dunglinson [n.d.], 1 TD, 5 AD (Box-folder 004-012)
  Re: Handwritten & typed transcriptions of Robley's letters from 1831-1833.
- Handwritten Notes [n.d.], 7 AN (Box-folder 004-013)
- Handwritten Notes [n.d.], 40 AN, 2 TN (Box-folder 004-014)
- Miscellaneous Typed Footnotes [n.d.], 4 TD (Box-folder 004-015)
- "Contents of the Volumes of the ANA by Dr. D" [n.d.], 1 TMs (Box-folder 004-016)
- Miscellaneous Footnotes [n.d.], 9 TD (Box-folder 004-017)
- Table of Contents [n.d.], 1 TMs (Box-folder 004-018)
- Miscellaneous Footnotes [n.d.], 4 TN, 1 AN (Box-folder 004-019)
- Index to the first seven volumes of Ana [n.d.], 1 TMs (Box-folder 004-020)
- Typed Manuscript: Appendix I [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN (Box-folder 004-021)
  Re: Dunglinson-Randall-Grisby Correspondence
- Typed Manuscript: Appendix II [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN (Box-folder 004-022)
  Re: Institutions to which Dunglinson belonged.
- Typed Manuscript: Appendix III [n.d.], 1 TD, 1 AN (Box-folder 004-023)
  Re: Original works issued by Dunglinson.
- Typed Manuscript: Appendix IV [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 004-024)
  Re: Works edited or translated or both by Dr. Dunglison.
- Typed Manuscript: Appendix V [n.d.], 1 TMs (Box-folder 004-025)
  Re: Journals edited by Dr. Dunglison.
- Typed Manuscript: Appendix VI [n.d.], 2 AN, 1 TMs (Box-folder 004-026)
  Re: Original essays & contributions to periodicals & other literature.
- Typed Manuscript: Appendix VII [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN (Box-folder 004-027)
  Re: Boyhood letters & a letter to his son Richard.
- Typed Manuscript: Appendix IX [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN, 1 AN (Box-folder 004-028)
  Re: Medical history of Andrew Jackson.
- Typed Mansuscript: Appendix [n.d.], 1 TMs (Box-folder 004-029)
  Re: "What a Gunshot-Wound Did For Science Half a Century Ago."
- Radbill's Introduction to "The Autobiographical Ana of Robley Dunglinson, M.D." October 8, 1961, 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 005-001)
  Typed introduction with handwritten edits.
- Footnotes, Chapter I [n.d.], 1 TMs, w/AN (Box-folder 005-002)
  Re: These footnotes are more indepth and extensive than the footnotes that appear in the published book.
- Footnotes, [Chapter II] [n.d.], 1 TMs w/ AN (Box-folder 005-003)
  Re: Footnotes are more indepth and extensive than the published footnotes.
- Footnotes, Chapter III [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN (Box-folder 005-004)
- Footnotes, Chapeter IV [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN (Box-folder 005-005)
- Editorial Comments for Chapter VI [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-006)
  Re: A few additional changes.
- Footnotes, Chapter VI [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN, 1 AN (Box-folder 005-007)
- Footnotes, Chapter VIII [Actually Chapter VII] [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN (Box-folder 005-008)
- Footnotes, Appendix VII [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 005-009)
- Letter from S[amuel] X. R[adbill] to Jerome J. Bylebyl May 4, 1967, 1 ALS (Box-folder 005-010)
  Re: About the Dunglison - Beaumont relationship.
- Appendix VIII: Dunglison and Beaumont [n.d.], 1 TMs (Box-folder 005-011)
  Re: This appendix deals with correspondence between Dunglinson and Dr. Beaumont; it was not included in the published book.
- Appendix IX: The Medical History of Andrew Jackson [n.d.], 1 TMs (Box-folder 005-012)
  Re: Explores Dunglison's relationship as a physician to Andrew Jackson; not included in the published book.
- Chapter I: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TMs w/AN (Box-folder 005-013)
  Re: Abbreviated footnotes with edits, which appear in the published book.
- Chapter II: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TMs (Box-folder 005-014)
- Chapter III: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TMs (Box-folder 005-015)
- Chapter IV: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TMs (Box-folder 005-016)
  Re: Abbreviated footnotes which appear in the published book.
- Chapter V: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TMs (Box-folder 005-017)
- Chapter VI: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TMs (Box-folder 005-018)
- Chapter VII: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TMs (Box-folder 005-019)
- Appendix I: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-020)
  Re: These footnotes appear in the published book.
- Appendix II: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-021)
- Appendix III: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-022)
- Appendix IV: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-023)
- Chapter I: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-024)
- Chapter II: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-025)
- Chapter III: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-026)
- Chapter IV: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-027)
- Chapter V: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-028)
- Chapter VI: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-029)
- Chapter VII: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-030)
- Appendix I: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-031)
- Appendix II: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-032)
- Appendix III: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-033)
- Appendix IV: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-034)
- Appendix VI: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-035)
- Appendix VII: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-036)
- Appendix VII: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-037)
- Page 7743 [Incomplete] [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 005-038)
- Miscellaneous pages [n.d.], 9 TD (Box-folder 005-039)
- Miscellaneous Pages [n.d.], 9 TD (Box-folder 005-040)
- Introduction [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 005-041)
  Re: Edited copy of Introduction.
- Portraits of Dunglison [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 005-042)
  Re: Edited version of portraits section in published book.
- Editorial Treatment [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 005-043)
  Re: Edited version.
- Acknowledgements [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 005-044)
- p. 774 - [Incomplete] [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-045)
- Chapter I: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 005-046)
- Chapter II: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 005-047)
- Chapter III: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 005-048)
- Chapter IV: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-049)
- Chapter V: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD w/ AN (Box-folder 005-050)
- Chapter VI: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD w/ AN (Box-folder 005-051)
- Chapter VII: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 005-052)
- Appendix I: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 005-053)
- Appendix II: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 005-054)
- Appendix III: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 005-055)
- Appendix IV: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 005-056)
- Appendix VI: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 005-057)
- Appendix VII: Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD w/AN (Box-folder 005-058)
- SXR 1902-1987: His Life and Work April 20, 1988, 1 TMs (Box-folder 006-001)
  Re: An appreciation for Samueal X. Radbill, M.D., distributed at the Thirteenth Radbill Lecture
- University of Virginia, Charlottesville [n.d.], 1 photo (reprint) (Box-folder 006-002)
- Architectural sketch: Model for Pavilion No. X [n.d.], 1 photo (reprint) (Box-folder 006-003)
- Architectural drawing: University of Maryland School of Medicine, 1812 [n.d.], 1 photo (reprint) (Box-folder 006-004)
- Anatomical Theatre [n.d.], 1 photo (reprint) (Box-folder 006-005)
- Title Page: New Dictionary of Medical Science & Literature [n.d.], 1 photo (Box-folder 006-006)
- Title Page: Human Physiology [n.d.], 1 photo (Box-folder 006-007)
- "The Following strictly private autobiographical Ana" [n.d.], 1 photo (Box-folder 006-008)
- Keswick from Greta Bridge [n.d.], 3 photo (reprint) (Box-folder 006-009)
- Student Admittance Card to one of Dunglison's lectures [n.d.], 1 photo (Box-folder 006-010)
- Handwritten page by Dunglinson [n.d.], 1 photo (Box-folder 006-011)
- Dunglinson's Medical Diploma from the University of Evlangen [n.d.], 2 reprint (Box-folder 006-012)
- Jefferson Medical College of Philadelphia [n.d.], 1 photo (reprint) (Box-folder 006-013)
- Letter from McD. to S[amuel] X. R[adbill] December 12, 1961, 1 TLS (Box-folder 006-014)
  Re: Provides a few suggestions regarding the Ana.
- Index: Deleted by A.P.S. [n.d.], 1 AN (Box-folder 006-015)
- Dunglison Prospects [n.d.], 1 AN (Box-folder 006-016)
- Editorial Notes on Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 006-017)
- Typed Intro with Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TMs (Box-folder 006-018)
- Typed Introduction with Footnotes [n.d.], 1 TMs (xerox) w/ AN (Box-folder 006-019)
  Re: Edits.
- Introduction [n.d.], 1 TD (Box-folder 006-020)
  Re: Brief intro about Dunglinson.
- Handwritten Introduction by Radbill [n.d.], 1 AD (Box-folder 006-021)
- Author's Copy of The Autobiographical Ana of Robley Dunglison, M.D. 1963, 1 TMs (Box-folder 006-022)
  Re: Cover & title page through p. 71.
- Author's Copy of The Autobiographical Ana of Robley Dunglison, M.D. 1963, 1 TMs (Box-folder 006-023)
  Re: pp. 72-137.
- Author's Copy of The Autobiographical Ana of Robley Dunglison, M.D. 1963, 1 TMs (Box-folder 006-024)
  Re: pp. 138-201.
- Author's Copy of the Index 1963, 1 TMs (Box-folder 006-025)